<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!--<?rfc strict="no"?> -->

<rfc category="bcp"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-kwatsen-netmod-artwork-folding-latest">
    <front>
        <title>Handling Long Lines in Artwork in Drafts</title>
        <author initials="K.W." surname="Watsen" fullname="Kent Watsen">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>kwatsen@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="Q.W." surname="Wu" fullname="Qin Wu">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <email>bill.wu@huawei.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Farrel" fullname="Adrian Farrel" >
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>afarrel@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
       </author>
       <author initials="B." surname="Claise" fullname="Benoît Claise" >
           <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems, Inc.">Cisco Systems,
           Inc.</organization>
           <address>
             <postal>
                 <street>De Kleetlaan 6a b1</street>
                 <city>1831 Diegem</city>
                 <country>Belgium</country>
             </postal>
             <phone>+32 2 704 5622</phone>
             <email>bclaise@cisco.com</email>
           </address>
    </author>  
        <date/>
        <area>gen</area>
        <workgroup>Internet Architecture Board (IAB)</workgroup>
        <keyword>artwork</keyword>
        <keyword>sourcecode</keyword>
        <abstract>
          <t>This document introduces a simple and yet time-proven strategy
          for handling long lines in artwork in drafts using a backslash
          ('\') character where line-folding has occurred.  The strategy
          works on any text based artwork, producing consistent results
          regardless the artwork content.  Using a per-artwork header,
          the strategy is both self-documenting and enables automated
          reconstitution of the original artwork.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
      <section title="Introduction">
        <t>Internet drafts many times contain artwork that exceed the 72
        character limit specified by RFC 7994 <xref target="RFC7994"/>.
        The "xml2rfc" utility, in an effort to maintain clean formatting,
        issues a warning whenever artwork lines exceed 69 characters.
        According to RFC Editor, there is currently no convention in
        place for how to handle long lines, other than clearly indicating
        that some manipulation has occurred.</t>

        <t>This document introduces a simple and yet time-proven strategy
        for handling long lines using a backslash ('\') character where
        line-folding has occurred.  The strategy works on any text based
        artwork, producing consistent results regardless the artwork 
        content.   Using a per-artwork header, the strategy is both
        self-documenting and enables automated reconstitution of the
        original artwork.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language" anchor="requirements-language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
        when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Goals">
        <section title="Automated folding of long lines in artwork">
          <t>Automated folding of long lines is needed in order to support
          draft compilations that entail a) validation of source input
          files (e.g., YANG, XML, JSON, ABNF, ASN.1) and/or b) dynamic
          generation of output (e.g., tree diagrams) that are stitched
          into the final draft to be submitted.</t>
          <t>Generally, in order for tooling to be able to process input
          files, the files must be in their original/natural state, which
          may include having some long lines.  Thus, these source files
          need to be modified before inclusion in the draft in order to
          satisfy the line length limits.  This modification SHOULD be
          automated to reduce effort and errors resulting from manual
          effort.</t>
          <t>Similarly, dynamically generated output (e.g., tree diagrams)
          must also be modified, if necessary, in order for the resulting
          I-D to satisfy the line length limits.  When needed, this effort
          again SHOULD be automated to reduce effort and errors
          resulting from manual effort.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Automated reconstitution of original artwork">
          <t>Automated reconstitution of the original artwork is needed to
          support validation of artwork extracted from drafts.  Already
          YANG modules are extracted from drafts and validated as part of
          the draft-submission process.  Additionally, there has been
          some discussion regarding needing to do the same for examples
          contained within drafts (<xref target="yang-doctors-list"/>).
          Thus, it SHOULD be possible to mechanically reconstitute artwork
          in order to satisfy the tooling input parsers.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Limitations">
        <section title="Doesn't work well on graphical artwork">
          <t>While the solution presented in this document will work on any
          kind of text-based artwork, it is most useful on artwork that
          represents sourcecode (e.g., YANG, XML, JSON, etc.) or, more
          generally, on artwork that has not been laid out in two dimensions
          (e.g., diagrams).</t>
          <t>The issue regards the readability of the folded artwork in the
          draft.  Artwork that is unpredictable is especially susceptible is
          looking bad when folded; falling into this category are most
          UML diagrams.  Artwork that is somewhat structured (e.g., YANG tree
          diagrams <xref target="RFC8340"/>) fair better when folded, as the
          eyes seem to be able to still see the vertical lines, even when
          they are interrupted.</t>
          <t>It is thus NOT RECOMMENDED to use the solution presented in
          this document on graphical artwork.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Doesn't work as well as format-specific options">
          <t>The solution presented in this document works generically 
          for all artwork, as it only views artwork as plain text.
          However, various formats sometimes have mechanisms that can
          be used to prevent long lines.</t>
          <t>For instance, some source formats allow any quoted string
          to be broken up into substrings separated by a concatenation
          character ('+'), any of which can by on a different line.</t>
          <t>In another example, some languages allow factoring out
          chucks of code out into "functions" or "groupings".  Using
          such call outs is especially helpful when in some deeply-nested
          code, as it typically resets the indentation back to the first
          column.</t>
          <t>As such, it is RECOMMENDED that authors do as much as
          possible within the selected format to avoid long lines.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Solution" anchor="solution">
        <t>The following two sections provide the folding and unfolding algorithms
        that MUST be implemented to align with this BCP.</t>
        <section title="Header" anchor="header">
          <t>Any artwork that has been folded as specificed by this document
          MUST contain the header described in this section.</t>
          <t>The header is two lines long.</t>
          <t>The first line is the following 53-character string that has been
          padded with roughly equal numbers of equal ('=') characters to reach
          the artwork's maximum line length.  This line is self-describing in
          three ways: use of '\' character, identification of BCP/RFC, and
          identification of what the maximum line length is for the artwork.
          Following is the mimimal header string (53-characters):</t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
=== NOTE: '\' line wrapping per BCP XX (RFC XXXX) ===
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>The second line is a blank line.  This line provides visual seperation
          for the readability.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Folding">
          <t>Scan the artwork to see if any line exceeds the desired maximum.
          If no line exceeds the desired maximum, exit (this artwork does not
          need to be folded).</t>
          <t>Ensure that the desired maximum is not less than then minumum
          header, which is 53 characters.  If the desired maximum is less
          than this minimum, exit (this artwork can not be folded).</t>
          <t>Scan the artwork to ensure no existing lines already end with
          a '\' character on the desired maximum column, as this would be
          lead to an ambiguous result.  If such a line is found, exit
          (this artwork cannot be folded).</t>
          <t>For each line in the artwork, from top-to-bottom, if the
          line exceeds the desired maximum, then fold the line at the
          desired maximum column by inserting the string "\\n"
          (backlash followed by line return) at the column before the
          maximum column.  Note that the column before needs to be used
          in order to enable the '\' character to be placed on the desired
          maximum column. The result of this operation is that the character
          that was on the maximum colomn is now the first character of the
          next line.</t>
          <t>Continue in this manner until reaching the end of the artwork.
          Note that this algorithm naturally addresses the case where the
          remainder of a folded line is still longer than the desired maximum,
          and hence needs to be folded again, ad infinitum.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Unfolding">
          <t>Scan the beginning of the artwork for the header described in
          <xref target="header"/>.  If the header is not present, starting
          on the first line of the artwork, exit (this artwork does not
          need to be unfolded).</t>
          <t>Caluculate the folding-column used from the length of the
          provided header.</t>
          <t>Remove the 2-line header from the artwork.</t>
          <t>For each line in the artwork, from top-to-bottom, if the line
          has a '\' on the folding-column followed by a '\n' character, then
          remove both the '\' and '\n' characters, which will bring up the
          next line, and then scan the remainder of the line to see if it
          again has a '\' after folding-column characters followed by a '\n'
          character, and so on.</t>
          <t>Continue in this manner until reaching the end of the artwork.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Example" anchor="example">
          <t>The following self-documenting example illustrates the result
          of the folding algorithm running over a specific artwork input.</t>
          <t>The specific input used cannot be presented here, as it would
          again need to be folded.  Alas, only the result can be provided.</t>
          <t>Some things to note about the following example:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>This artwork is exactly 69 characters wide, the widest
              possible before `xml2rfc` starts to issue warnings.</t>
              <t>The line having the 'x' character on the 69th column
              would've been illegal input had the '\' been used.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(refs/folding-needed.txt.folded)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-cons">
        <t>This BCP has no Security Considerations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-cons">
        <t>This BCP has no IANA Considerations.</t>
      </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

      <references title="Normative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
      </references>

      <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7994.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8340.xml"?>
        <reference anchor="yang-doctors-list" target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/msg/yang-doctors/DCfBqgfZPAD7afzeDFlQ1Xm2X3g">
          <front>
            <title>[yang-doctors] automating yang doctor reviews</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>


      <!-- APPENDICIES -->
      <section title="POSIX Shell Script" anchor="foobar">
        <t>This non-normative appendix section includes a shell script
        that can both fold and unfold artwork based on the solution
        presented in this document.</t>
        <t>As a testament for the simplicity of this solution, note
        that at the core of the script are the following two one-liners:
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
For folding:
  gsed "/.\{$testcol\}/s/\(.\{$foldcol\}\)/\1\\\\\n/g"

For unfolding:
  gsed ":x; /[^\t]\\{$foldcol\\}\\\\\$/N; s/\\\\\n/\t/; tx; s/\t//g"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>Disclaimer: this script has the limitation of disallowing
        the input file from containing any TAB ('\t') characters.</t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>=====START SCRIPT=====</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(fold-artwork.sh)
]]></artwork>
            <postamble>=====END SCRIPT=====</postamble>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
        <t>The authors thank the RFC Editor for confirming that there are no set convention today for handling long lines in artwork. </t>
      </section>
    </back>

</rfc>
